<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A frutfull sermon of the moost euangelicall wryter M. Luther, made of the angelles vpo[n] the. xviii. chapi. of Mathew translated out of laten in to Englyshe</title>
            <title>Predigt von den Engeln. English.</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16983</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108954</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844606</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844606</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9435</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06510)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9435)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 240:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A frutfull sermon of the moost euangelicall wryter M. Luther, made of the angelles vpo[n] the. xviii. chapi. of Mathew translated out of laten in to Englyshe</title>
                  <title>Predigt von den Engeln. English.</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
                  <author>Foxe, John, 1516-1587.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Paules churche yerde, at the syngne of saynt Augustyne by [J. Mychell for] Hugh Syngleton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Prynted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Eine Predigt von den Engeln.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: I. Fox.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name supplied and publication date conjectured by STC (addendum).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-D E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XVIII --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9435:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9435:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A Frutfull ſermon of the mooſt Euan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelicall wryter M.
Luther / made of the Angelles vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xviii. chapi. of Mathew tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlated
out of laten into Englyſhe. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
            <p>Prynted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les churche yerde / at the ſyngne of
ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne by Hugh Syngleton.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9435:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9435:2"/>
            <head>To his Chriſten frende &amp; brother Henry Ruoche the
tranſlator wyſſheth abundaunce of grace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Culde wyſhe eyther all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be lerned in the
vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtandynge of laten, or elles lerned men more diligent in tranſlatyng
to the vul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gare tonge ſuche thynges as our ignoraunte brethren do not
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue, bothe for the readynge of many other excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bokes in this tonge
wryten, &amp; namely of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Luther, whoſe bookes I iudge very expedyent
and alſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Chryſtes churche, bothe for the moſte ſwete
conſolacions in them conteyned, &amp; farther for ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of many
myſteryes, moche conuenyent to be knowen of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chriſten man. Amongeſt
which other thys lytell boke or ſermon<pb facs="tcp:9435:3"/>made of the Angelles I
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out and tranſlate for you
(gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll Henry) with what dexterite I can not ſay, truly of a good
pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe &amp; a ſtudiouſe mynd towarde you, to do you good, to thentent
not only yt ſhuld be a teſtimoniall of my hart I beare vnto you, but alſo
and moch rather an occaſion whereby to encourage &amp; ſtyrevp thys
propenſite and forwardnes of yours ſo happely begonne, and godly continuyng
/ I wyll not ſay this author in all poynts to ſtand vp ryght and
abſolutely, as in the ſacramentes, but what humane wryter hathe there euer
bene but ſome defaute he hathe left behynd hym. Alſo Peter was not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out
his reprehenſion. In euery thyng the beſt is to be taken. Verely in this
matter I doubt not, you wyll lyke hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well as he is worthy. Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes grace
with you. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Stepney.</dateline> 
               <signed>Yours I. Fox.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9435:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An homelie of doctor Marten Luther made of the Angelles on
Mychaelmaſday vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the goſpell of Mathewe xviii. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the goſpell this daye we heare Chriſte make mencion of
Angelles, for whom this preſent feaſte of ſaynct Michaell was
iſtituted, and not ſo muche for thys angell only ſaynct Michaell, nor the
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angelles, but chefely for the honor of oure lord god the maker of all
the angelles. And that not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration. bycau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe it is
very neceſſary in Chriſtes churche a ryght knowllege &amp; doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
<pb facs="tcp:9435:4"/>of the Angelles to be a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whych thyng is
alſo very profitable and bryngyth no ſmalle conſolation to know what is
theyr office and dutye, no leſſe then it is to know what is the offi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of
a father, of a mother, of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, of a mayde or any other ſuch lyke.
For yf ſo be it the office of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery perſon be not knowen preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly
wherto he is called, &amp; to what he is ordenid, one ſhal medle with ones
office &amp; an other ſhall medle with an others, none knowyng his propre
fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctione what he hathe to do, thus muſt nedes be that all runne in hepes, in
tumultes, &amp; in confuſion to gether. Wherfore it is neceſſary that we
knowe what the propre office and fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctione is of Angelles, to do. The ignorance
wherof, bryngith in many abſurd cogitationes and fonde fables a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſte
chriſten peple, as we ſee<pb facs="tcp:9435:4"/>planly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this feaſt, which hath ben
a feaſt nowe many yeares full of Idolatrie byſydes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vaine fables and
feyned myracles which haue bene brought in of the hyll Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garus, that is
called ſaynct micha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>els mount. And of ſaynet michals letteres, with ſuch
lyke manifeſt foolyſhe and tryflynge lyes ſpred through all the worlde,
by reſon wherof we haue fallen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyp of god the maker of all,
to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhyppyng of Angelles, which he hathe created. Therfore we do not
kepe thys feaſte but only for thys cauſe, to lerne &amp; know what the
Angelles doo, wherabout thei goo, and what is the charge wher unto they be
aſſigned of god, to the entent that after we ſhal be cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tefyed &amp;
inſtructed in the matter, we ſhall begynne to render than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to god for
his Angelles, ſo as we do thanke his maieſte for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng<pb facs="tcp:9435:5"/>of the
ſunne &amp; mone, for ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng vs peace, for gyuyng vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, for
ſettyng vs lawes, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and for all oure other benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes which he
ſendyth to vs &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruyth, not that we do worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne or
the moone, with ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but that we do marke and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidre the
wonderfull worke and or dinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of almyghtie god therin, &amp; ſo in the
ſunne prayſe him that made the ſunne, glorifie him and worſhyp hym. And
ſo I ſay lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angelles, that we muſt lerne and knowe theyr
office, their dewtie, &amp; function wherunto they ſerue, that in
conſyderyng &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of this, we ſhall gyue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to god,
aſcribyng all thys be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite whole to god, ſo that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honor &amp;
glory hereof may redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vnto him, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is only dewe.</p>
            <p>Therfore fyrſt of all we muſte know and be ſuered that there
bee Angelles, not only good angelles<pb facs="tcp:9435:5"/>but alſo badde. There haue
bene chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue thought as the ſaduceys dyd, nother Angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
nor ſpirites to be. And I my ſelfe haue herde ſome to play the ſaduces,
which haue not bene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to blaſpheme and to denie and thynke neither
Angelles nor ſprits to be. But a true chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought not to doubt but
that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuyll is naturally an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell made, euen as ſaynct
Mycha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell is created an Angel. But their office &amp; doyngs be much dyuers,
for lyke as a noughty tirant hath autorrite and power as well as a good prynce,
but the one abuſith hys power to oppreſſe his ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other
vſeth it as he ſhulddo to the preſeruation and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modite of his realme.
So is it betwixt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll and the good Angelle. Beſydes theſe men that
thynke there be no deuylles. There be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<pb facs="tcp:9435:6"/>other wich not
w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandyng they beleue there be deuylles, yet do not thynke they be ſo
neyghe, nor ſo ſore agaynſt vs, but whan they here any ſpekynge of the
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uylle, they imagine him an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth or a thouſand miles of from vs. And
ſo by reaſon we do not know nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how nyghe and redy the deuyll is
agaynſte vs at all tymes, ne can not perceiue ſo well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great benefites
which god ſhewyth to vs by hys Angelles. Lyke as he which neuer felt death
nor taſted the bytternes therof, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not tell how pretious and ſwete is
lyfe. And as he whiche neuer felt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not iuge how good and pretious a
thyng is bredde, nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not eſteme the valow therof, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man which euer
thynkyth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll ſo ferre abſent from him, doth not greatly regarde the
dayly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the holy Angelles of<pb facs="tcp:9435:6"/>god, nor can not
eſteme it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngly. But euery good chriſten man muſt thus thynke with
hym ſelfe that he ſytteth in the myddeſt of the deuylles, which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a
great multitude incloſe him and beſege hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> round about. And that Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is
more nere hym than hys coote, than his ſhirte, yea than his ſkyn and hys
owne fleſhe, euermore he is aboute vs, for vs to feyght w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> and to ſtryue
agaynſte. That the deuyll is ſo nygh and redy aboute vs, that oure germayne
prouerbe doth ſhewe and teſtifey, whoſe me nyng is thys. Yt nedyth not to
paynt the deuyll vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dore, me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng therby y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuyll is neygh ynough
oure houſe, though he be not paynted at the dore. Therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re fyrſt of all we
muſt knowe thys and ſo perſuade our ſelues, that there be deuylles, and
that they be more neghe vnto vs tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſhyrt<pb facs="tcp:9435:7"/>is to oure body.
And thys ſaynct Peter doth well teſtefye which is no lyer ſayng, in the
v. ca.<note place="margin">Pet. 5.</note> Be you ſober and be ware, for your
aduer ſarie the deuyll goeth aboute lyke a roryng lyon whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure.
Theſe wordes were not ſpoken of no dronkerd, nor is no fooles bolte, as we
be wonte to ſay, but they were ſpoken of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters owne mouth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy
gooſt, nether in geeſt nor in ſport, but in erneſt as erneſtly as he
culde ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Be ſober &amp; beware ſayth he, as thoughe he wold
ſay, do not ſo imagine with youre ſelues, as thoughe youre enemye were
farre from you. Your enemye is a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and a perpetuall aduerſary
euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more agaynſte you, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all hatred and malice he can, whoſe porpoſe
is nothyng els but to dyſtroy you both body and ſoule. Where is he than
wylt thou ſay. Peter tellyth<pb facs="tcp:9435:7"/>the. He runnyth about the, ſayth he
/ what doyth he, what ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyth he runnynge about vs? Peter ſhewyth the, he
ſekyth / ſayth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whome he may deuoure. Here you haue the deuyl
paynted in his colours. Ye hard before that there is a deuyll, here you ſee
what a thyng he is, how malitious, how peſtilent, and vexed agaynſte vs,
which euery day doth no thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g els but ſtudieth how to deuoure vs &amp; to
dyſtroy vs, this is all hys ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; purpoſe, to worke oure
dyſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euermore ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng about vs, with ſuch hatred and malice that
no man can expreſſe yt, euen lyke a roryng lyon he ragyth about, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to
ſay / what ſoeuer thou doeſt, whether thou thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kyſt or ſpeakyſt, or
what ſo euer thou ſettyſt vpon to do, other to begyn a thynge or to
fynyſh any worke, the deuyll is euer preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſekyng all meanes and
<pb facs="tcp:9435:8"/>occaſion to ſtoppe to troble the, &amp; to lett the. But fewe
me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleue it, for yf they dyd, they wold not lyue ſo ſecurely &amp; ſo
carles as they do. And thys is the cauſe that we ſee all the world ſo
full of ſtryffe, deba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, hatred, enuey, pryde, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes luſtes, and
ſuche other vices. And yet how ſecurely &amp; how negli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gently men lyue, as
though they had clene deuoured and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed the deuyll. And here is to be
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there be two ſortes of men poſſeſſed with the
deuyll. Sum be poſſeſſed bodely in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may planly perceiue the good
wyll of the deuyll toward vs, as in Matthe. viii.<note place="margin">Mat.
8.</note> What pleaſure it was to him in punyſhyng the poore miſer not
only with one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, but withe an whole hoſte of deuylles. This is the good
wyll he beryth toward vs. Is not this a poyſoned and excedynge malice
<pb facs="tcp:9435:8"/>that the wyked fynd beryth to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynde, in that we ſee hym ſo
vexe thys one ſylly ſoule with ſo many thouſand of deuylles.
Forthermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re we may ſe alſo ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, what mynde he beryth towarde
vs, by ſuche poſſeſſed perſons that ley in theyr monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.
Theſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch other exſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples do well declare the myſcheuous fury and
the byrning hatered of the wycked ſpirite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs, whiche hathe no
other deſyre nor pleaſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he delyteth in, but only in our
deſtruction, ſo that he may dyſtroy our bodies, &amp; bryng oure ſoules
to euerlaſtyng peryll. Secondarly there is alſo an other ſort, of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
which bee pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely and ſpiritually poſſeſſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll, as
theſe which be enta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled with couitouſnes with hatred, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> enuey, with
luſtes, and fylthy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyers, with other lyke vices, and yet for al that
lyue in ſuch ſecurite<pb facs="tcp:9435:9"/>and ſo recheles as though the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll
were a thouſande leges of, &amp; had nothyng adoo with them. Yf any external
grefe or ſeknes ſhuld chaunce to oure bodyes, we ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſtreyght to the
phiſition for his cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell and ſuccore. But to ſeke any remedy
agaynſt oure inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, agaynſte oure couituſnes, our malice,
our enuye and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mo, to ſeke remedy I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt theſe
that we may lerne to refrayne oure ſynfull lyuyng, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof we paſſe not a
butte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor ons do mynde any ſuche thyng. And why ſo? bycauſe no man wyll
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that the deuyll is ſo nye and euer aboute vs. Therfore let vs lerne
as I ſayde, and conſider dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently what maner a thyng the deuyll is, how
fears, howe mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, how myghty, howe ſuttell and crafty he is, what power
he hath to hurt both body and ſoule.<pb facs="tcp:9435:9"/>He bringeth in to our
ſoules falſe and erroneus doctrine, deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fylthy deſyres w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
other lyke, and all to plucke awaye our fayth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, and to caſte vs in to
infidelite and waueryng, or els to put in to our myndes cold fylthy, &amp;
vayne cogitations, that by that meanes he may caſte vs in to ſecurite and
necligens. I knowe yt and dare ſpeke it by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for oftymes I do
ſenſibly feale the deuyll ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyng and lettyng my cogitations my
purpoſe, and my labors. I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not doo and fyniſh all thynges ſo as I
wold, by the reaſon he ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyth me and hyndreth me. Many tymes yt is my
mynd to do thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges with more feruent ſtudy with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hede and diligence than
I doo, but by the reaſon of his impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and ſtoppes of the deuyll I
ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not imploy my matters ſo always with ſuch perfection as I wolde:
<pb facs="tcp:9435:10"/>So than after that he hathe thus poſſeſſed the
ſpirituall inynde of a man, than after he doth alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and dothe noy
the body other with peſtilence, with famyn, with warre, with ſlawghter, or
with ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calamite or other, which he hathe an infinite ſort. All theſe
myſchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues dothe the deull ſtyre vp, he is only the worker of all theſe
euyls. One brekyth hys legge, an other is drowned, an other doth murder an
other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth aduoutre, and ſo forth. Who is the doer of all theſe, who
is the motioner and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leder to all theſe? Who but only the deuyll? And thys
all we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetue, we ſee yt with oure eys, we feele yt with our handes, and
yet neeligently, howe ſecuerly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out hede or drede we lyue? And what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
cauſe of this? Truly nothing els but as I ſayd, bycauſe we ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gine the
deuyll to be farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.<pb facs="tcp:9435:10"/>But we farre deceiue oure ſelues.
Forſothe he is harde by the, and is ouer thy head, &amp; is aboute the, and
about all men. And thys god wyllyth and doeth ſuffer it to be, by this meanes
to kepe vs in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are, that we beware &amp; take heede to our ſelues, and that
through ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſcite of ſuche greart perylles we ſhuld be dryuen to flee to
our lord god for ſuccoure. yf there were no deuylles, truly we ſhuld be
colde, necligent, ſlacke, ſecure omiſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all care and feare. And
yet for all thys, for all thyſe wyckyd ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rittes aboute vs, for all
theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamites &amp; vexationes, for the wret chednes and miſeries, for
all theſe euyls &amp; diſpleaſures that we haue God can ſkarſly dryue
vs to call vpon hym, to flee vnto hym, and to crye for ſuccoure. O father of
heauen, Come helpe vs, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, than what wold we doo yf<pb facs="tcp:9435:11"/>there were no deuylle at all? Therfore principally and fyrſte of all
we muſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and knowe that we ſyt not here in the myddle of
roſes, or in a garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is ſaffe and ſuer from all perilles and
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytes of our ennemies. If the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll dyd ſeduce Adam and Eue in
paradiſe, alſo yf he trobled ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other good men and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god.
Moreouer yf he dyd not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to tempte Chriſte himſelfe both god and the
ſonne of god, thynke not thy ſelfe ſo ſuer nor ſo well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſed,
that he wyll be affrayd of the. Therefore lett vs pray vnto god diligently and
feruently that he wyll gyue vs grace to be ware and to take hede of oure
ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the craftie aſſaltes &amp; ſugge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtion of the
deuill, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he caſt vs not in diſperation or incredulite. At the generall
counſell kepte in the cetie Anguſta how he went about<pb facs="tcp:9435:11"/>all that
he myght poſſiblely, to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drawe vs agayne from oure true fayth, &amp; to
bryng vs agayn in to our olde errors. So &amp; yf hys pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe had
proſpered and gone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he wold alſo haue wrought more myſcheyf in
ſtyrring vp bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taylles, and bloodſhed, &amp; tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people.
But we muſt knowe thys moreouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoughe there be neuer ſo many euyll
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rittes agaynſte vs that worke vs ſorow, yet be there many moo good
Angels agayne which ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe and lett the pourpoſe of theſe wycked fyndes,
kepynge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendynge vs agaynſt them. The wycked ſpirites do nother
ſlepe nyght nor daye, euer watchynge and ſtudyenge howe to brynge in
Idolatrie, &amp; ſo to caſt oure ſoules into perpetuall diſtruccion,
and then after to do ſum vylany to our bodyes, to oure goodes, or good
<pb facs="tcp:9435:12"/>name: So vnles that God agayn had other rulers, &amp; an other
kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, in the whiche were other more valiant ſpirites than theſe,
truely the deuyll wolde neyther leue vs wyfe, chyldren nor houſe ſtandynge,
not the momente of an hower, but wolde dyſtroye, wolde ouerturne, confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de,
and aboliſhe all together: ſuche malyce and ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred he hath agaynſt
mankynde, that by his good wyll thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not haue one foote of ground
to ſtande vpon. And it greueth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euyll that thou haſte thyne eyes, thyne
armes, thy legges, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thy lymmes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf he myght haue his wyll and
God wolde ſo permytte hym, he wold denumme the of al, yea and not leaue the
one cowe, or an oxe, or a horſe to helpe the with, fynally yf that he were
ſuffered to worke his pleaſure he wolde not ſuffer not ſo moche as
<pb facs="tcp:9435:12"/>a ſtafe to ſtande in his place, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any man to continue
his lyfe the ſpace of halfe an howre. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore where as theſe thinges do
not ſo com to paſſe, and where as thou ſeeſt kyngdomes, and common
wealthes to remayne and ſtande whole in theyr ryghte forme and ſtate with
out any ſuche perturba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, where as thou ſeeſt any cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, ſhepe,
or oxen to lyue, or any ſuche thynge whiche doth ſeruyce to man (whiche
thynge greueth the deuyll ſore for he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not abyde any thynge to be ſafe
that pertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to man) be that mayſt thou well perceyue that there is a
more ſtrong and more valiant a power ordeyned of God, for to preſerue &amp;
defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vs agaynſt ſo wycked and furious maladies of our enmies. Alſo
where thou ſeeſt any good man to lyue in fayth and feare of God whiche
fauer and loue the<pb facs="tcp:9435:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>goſpell, by that thou mayſt well
perceyue and knowe that there is an other power ordayned and ſet vp of God
agaynſt the deuyll to withſtand and reſiſte &amp; to brynge to nought
his workes and his ſubtylties. For marke well the wordes of ſaynt Peter / 
he calleth hym our aduerſarie ſo infuſe and vexed agaynſt vs ſekynge
about lyke a roryng lyon whom he may deuoure. Then howe can he with his good
wyll ſuffre any thynge to remayne whole or ſafe? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeynge the
deuyll is ſo promt and ſo redy to hurte vs by all the meanes and
occaſions he can, and yet is put ſo ofte beſyde his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (by
reaſon that God doth ſo ſtoppe hym through his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) thou
oughteſt therfore euer to gyne thankes to God, that thy wyfe and chyldren do
lyue &amp; that thyne houſe is not plucked ouer<pb facs="tcp:9435:13"/>thyne heade. For
our defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, oure ſtrength were nothyng to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll. If there were nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
in him but only hys malice and hys wyll to hurt vs, yet were not we able to
reſiſte the ſame. But now byſyds this malicious &amp; ſet wyll
agaynſt vs, in this alſo he preualyth and paſſyth vs, in wyt, craft
policie, and ſubtilte, wherei all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaynctes be nothyng to be compared
with him. He hath the ſcriptures at his fyngars ende. He knowyth all the
bible better than all Paris or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie. Whoſoeuer dothe enter in
diſputation with him is quycly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome, there is none in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world able to
holde argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation with hym. Beſydes thys ſuche is hys myght and power,
that all myght of men and power of all the world is nothyng in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paryſon.
Set all the turkes, all the emperours, all the rulers, kynges, and princes,
<pb facs="tcp:9435:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>in all the whole worlde to gether, he is able to diſtroy
them &amp; blow them downe with turnynge of an hande. The cauſe nowe why he
doth not ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth not dyſtroy all thinges after his mynd &amp; wyll,
yt is through the benefyte and the preſeruation of good Angelles which do
reſiſt and withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hym that he can not ſo exerciſe hys ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny as
he wold. And ſo for this purpoſe be the Angelles ordened to withſtande
the deuyll &amp; to kepe hym ſhort. Euen lyke as a good prince hathe hys
officers vnder him, ſuch whom as he apoyntyth and ſettyth ouer his countres
and cities, agaynſte theues and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers. And yet though the ſame
officers take neuer ſo muche hede ouer the kynges ſubiectes, yet can they
not choſe, do beſt they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me thefe or other wyll come in, and
do ſome robry / whereby we<pb facs="tcp:9435:14"/>may wel perceiue, that the theues mynd
and good wyll is to do mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, yf he myght be ſuffered. And ſo is it here in
lyke maner. God ſome tymes doth gyue ſome permiſſion to euyll
ſpirittes, but yet he hathe hys good Angelles agayn, for to kepe vs and
defende vs agaynſte fury and violence. Thus euery prynce, euery citeſyn,
euery houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, brefuely euery chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hathe hys good Angelles
aſſined vnto hym, for to ſaue hym and to preſerue him, as Chriſt
teſtyfyeth in the goſpell ſaynge. Theire An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles in heauen do ſee the
face of my father which is in heauen. Theſe wordes verely do well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
the great and meruelous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, loue, &amp; tendernes that god hath vpon vs.
And theſe wordes ſhulde diligently be ſhewed &amp; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in to
childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they myght learne and know the office of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles,<pb facs="tcp:9435:15"/>and accept theyr benefite, and gyue god thankes therfore. The deuyll
is a greate enimy to all children, and yt greuyth hym much wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſeyth them
be borne in to the world, to grow vp and to proſper. And for this cauſe
dothe he many tymes frey women great with child and doth caſte them in to
feare. How be yt good Angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les be preſent and redy to ſuccore and kepe
them that they take no harme. Theſe thynges be preuie and preuely done that
we can not ſee them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our eys. In lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he poſſeſſyth men
preuely and after aſecret faſhyon, as wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he bryngyth a mans mynd to
co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uytuſnes, he putteth in to his hart this perſuaſion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he makyth hym
beleue he doth it for an honeſt pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, for the neceſſyte of hys
lyfe, to prouyde for hym ſelfe &amp; for hys houſholde, &amp; ſo thynkyth
he doth<pb facs="tcp:9435:15"/>very well, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll to be ferre from hym. Thus doth
the deuyll poſſeſſe theſe couytus perſons ſo preuely, that they
can ſcarſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him in theyr mynd, much les can they ſee him with
theyr bodely eys. And ſo doth he alſo blynd and wyche oure prynces hartes,
put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng in to them this perſuaſion &amp; thought, that they wage battayle
agaynſt other prynces, nother for hatred, nor enuye nor for any reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gans or
haſtynes of theyr mynde, but only for a ryght quarell, for Iuſtice and
peace. This is theyr pretence where w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they cloke theyr tyranny &amp; grefe or
grouge of theyr mynde. And theſe ſuggeſtions of the deuyll, yet ſeme to
them to be honeſt and very Iuſt quarelles. They thynke nothig les the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
theſe cogitations to come of the deuyll. And lyke as the euyll ſpirit dothe
preuely &amp; inwardly poſſeſſe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<pb facs="tcp:9435:16"/>ſo do the good
Angelles alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely &amp; ſecretly miniſter their helpe and ſuccore.
And lyke as the euyll ſpirit caſtyth in hys furye dartes preuely in to the
hart of man, ſo lykewyſe haue the good Angelles agayn theyr good &amp;
holſum dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort vs with. And whan ſo euer the euyl angell doth
tempt vs, they be euer redy to ſtope him, &amp; defende vs ſpeakyng thus
vnto vs in our hartes. Not ſo. Not ſo. Muche lyke as yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld falle
in to a depe water, and be in the ioperdy of drouni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, a other ſhuld runne to
take by the hande and to drawe him out of the water. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo do good Angelles
to vs, pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng vs bake, and callyng vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, ſayng thus inwardly in our hartes. Thou muſt take heede of
that. In no caſſe thou muſt do ſo. It is not meet nor laufull ſo to
do. And thus do the good Angelles<pb facs="tcp:9435:16"/>helpe vs, &amp; ſtope the
deuyll, that he take not our fayth from vs, nor haue his purpoſe of vs.
Therfore we vſe to ſay, and it is well ſayd. Thou haddyſt a good &amp;
a truſty Angell to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this day / where by is ſygnified, that no wytt
nor powre of man could turne awaye that euyll and myſchefe, vnleſſe the
good Angelles had ben redy with theyr ayde and cuſtodie / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that
they had eſpyed out and throwne downe the ingyns, decey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and craftes of
the deuyll, thou ſhuldeſt other peryſhe myſerable, or elles
ſhuldeſt be brought in to ſum great calamite. And this is that we meane
wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſay: Thou was bleſſed this day and kepte of a good Angell: and
ſo it is trewe: for vnleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good Angelles ſhuld preſerue vs, all
ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of wretched<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in the world ſhuld lyght vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, throught the
procurement of<pb facs="tcp:9435:17"/>the deuyl: wherfore let vs lerne to know, and
thankfully to accepte, this hye office and benefytt of the holly Angelles.
Alſo lett vs lerne this, that the wycked angelles do worke and go about
nothyng els, but only howe to hurt vs to vexe vs, &amp; to bryng vs in to all
trobles he can. But lyke as theſe euyll an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles be allways redy to harme
vs, ſo be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good Angelles agayn euer redy to helpe vs, that we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
not the truyth, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly ſtycke to yt, and that we haue and kepe our
lyues, oure bodys, oure wyffes, and children, breuely, all that we haue,
ſayffe &amp; whole, from the hurtyng of the deuyll. Thus the cauſe then why
all the worlde is not ſett on fyere, all is not caſte in heepes, that any
cities, any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men weithes, any realmes, any vyllages, be not deſtroyed,
caſte downe and ouer thrown, all thys<pb facs="tcp:9435:17"/>comyth through the helpe
and ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holly Angelles. Theſe good Angelles be much more pru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent,
polityke, and wittie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, wycked ſpirittes bee: by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thei
haue a glaſſe to loke in, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wycked ſpirites haue not. This
glaſſe is the face and the fruition of the father almyghtie. Forther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more
the good Angelles be much more of power tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other angelles be. For they be
euer in preſence &amp; in ſeruice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is almyghtie. Wherfore let
vs gyue euerlaſting thankes vnto God for theſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ſuche
miniſters, and poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes which he hath ordened for vs, to kepe vs, and to
preſerue vs in all places, which thinge they doo bothe diligently and
gladly.</p>
            <p>Furthermore we muſte vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande alſo, that theſe
angelles be not to be worſhypped, nor muſte we put oure truſte in them as
we<pb facs="tcp:9435:18"/>haue done in tymes paſte, for we fynde in ſcryptures that
they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wolde ſuffre them ſelues to be worſhypped, but euermore haue
gyuen that honour onely to God, They prayſe and laude God and thancke him
that they were made for vs. For as I ſayde they be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites made and
created of God on ly for this to ſerue vs and to helpe vs: Lyke the ſame
maner we pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe and thanke God, that he made this comfortable ſunne for
vs, the moone, wyne, bread, and all other maner of thinges. Euen lykewyſe
ought we to offer vp to hym im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall thankes for his good An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelles, and
ſumtymes amonge to bruſt out with ſome ſuche prayer / thankes and
prayſe to the, heauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly father, for that thou doeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs, kepe vs,
and gouerne vs ſo dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly throughe thy holly an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelles, &amp; that thou
hayſt ordened<pb facs="tcp:9435:18"/>ſuch pouers and ſo myghtie prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ouer vs.
&amp;.c. So whan thou gyuyſt god thankys after this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner I thynke thou
doyſt prayſe &amp; worſhipe the Angelles ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. Nowe to proue
that the Angelles be ſuche maner of ſpirittes as we haue ſhewed, it is
euede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in many places of the ſcripture as in Luc. the xii. where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Angelles apering to the ſhepperds &amp; ſhewyng them the byrth of
Chriſte, dyd ſyng the goodly ſonge <hi>Gloria in excelſis deo et in
terra pax hominibus bona voluntas.</hi> That is glory be to God aboue, peace in
earth, good wyll amonge men. It is a prouerbe amongſt vs. As the hart
thynkyth, ſo the tonge ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth. And ſo here, the Angelles ſpeake and
deſyre the honour and prayſe of god: then that we may ſee theyr hart and
good wyl to vs ward, they pray next that peace be in earth: for yt greuyth them
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng more whan they ſee ſuche<pb facs="tcp:9435:19"/>warres, &amp; battayles among
men, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſe any calamite or diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion among vs, when they ſee
any houſe brenne, or a mans oxe dye: For theyr nature and harte is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge
elles but peace, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all their wyſſhe and prayer is to haue
peace, quyetnes, health, &amp; goodnes to all men: the deuylles nature is this,
and this is all hys endeuer to plucke men from god. Contrarywiſe the good
Angelles do euer ſeeke and couitte that we ſhuld honoure god and loue hym.
The deuyll is our aduerſary, and therfore nothyng doth greue hym more, then
whan he ſeyth vs be in peace. Agayn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles doo wiſhe and reioyſe in
nothyng more, then whan they ſee the worlde bent to peace &amp; concord:
other els yf there be no concord, yt is our owne faut we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blame none but our
ſelues. For god can no otherwiſe debate<pb facs="tcp:9435:19"/>and reſtrayne oure
wantonneſſe, hedynes, &amp; our malicious nature.</p>
            <p>The thyrde thynge that the An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelles wyſhe for amonge men, is
good wyll, that is to ſay, that they wyll take well in worth what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
God ſendeth other good or badde: And that they wyll humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit them
ſelues to the wyll of God, and euery man be content with his ſtate and
fortune, taking his croſſe paciently what ſoeuer God ſendeth. Here in
theſe ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res you ſe the Angelles deſcrybed vnto you of an other
forte, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſophiſters and ſcoole men haue taught you in tymes
paſt. As whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re I haue ſhewed you howe. S. Peter hath deſcrybed the
deuyll, where as he fyrſt calleth hym our aduerſarie, and afterward
payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him in his colours, notefieng hym to walke about lyke a roring Lyon,
ſekynge whom he maye de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoure.<pb facs="tcp:9435:20"/>By theſe wordes of S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
you maye ſe hym moche more playnly and lyuely paynted vnto you, than yf I
ſhulde dyſpute and muſe with my ſelfe neuer ſo long, what an head or
noſe he hathe, or whether he hathe ſuche clawes or not as we paynt him to
haue. And yf thou wylt ſe the trewe &amp; playne fygure of the deuyll,
Imagyne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſelfe ſuche a maner of a man that is all wycked, all gyuen
to noughtines, malicious and full of ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kore, of a miſcheuous mynde and
ſtomacke, craftie, ſottyll, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytefull, all ſet to hurte and noye men.
And ſo ſhalt thou ſe the true proporcion and fiſnamie of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyll.
On the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary ſyde the good angels is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge els, but a mynd or an hart
which is perfytly good and louyng. As yf thou couldyſt fynd or woldyſt
imagine with thy ſelfe ſuch a perſon, which were all<pb facs="tcp:9435:20"/>nothyng
els but ſwetenes, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, cumlynes, and fryndlynes, whoſe mynde and
ſtomake were moſt meeke moſt gentyll, moſt her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, and kynd, ſymple
with out all fraude or gyle, of moſte ſupreme wiſdom &amp; knowlege. And
ſo ſhalt thou haue the very ſhape and ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of a good Angell. Wherfore
ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue they their name gyuen to them: for this worde angell in greke is that
whiche we call in englyſhe a meſſenger or an embaſſadore, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they be ſent of God. The ſcripture dothe not gyue them theyr name, of their
nature or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance wherof they be made (ſaue only that it callyth them
ſpirites) but it gyuyth them theyr names of theire office and miniſtery.
And therfore we cal them angelles, not as concernyng theyr ſubſtance or
nature wherof they be created, but as concernyng theyr office which<pb facs="tcp:9435:21"/>they be appoynted to. Wherfore we ought to loue thys name An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, and
to make much of it. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am greatly delyted with it, I can not tell what
other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, and do embrace it with all my hart. Nowe yf they be the
meſſyngers and embaſſadours of oure lorde god, then what thyng do they,
or wherfore doth god ſend them: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thou agayn. They do gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vs,
they kepe vs and preſerue vs: for that cauſe be they ſent, and that is
theyr office to do, to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſe the commaundement of god that is gyuen
them to do: that is: to ſtoppe the workes of the deuyll, to turne away euyll
chanſes, that houſes or ſtreetes be ſett on fyre, that our catell be
not deuoured of wyld beſtes, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſchape drow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge with ſuch lyke
thynges. Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo the euyll ſpiritt hath his name, and is called the deuyll,
that is,<pb facs="tcp:9435:21"/>acouſar or a damner: for that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature and all the
ſtudy of him, to accuſe, to blame to damne or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert, to make the
worſte of euery thyng that we doo. He is called al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo an Angell that is a
meſſynger: but an yll meſſynger &amp; a wycked. And well the grecyans
haue gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym this name <hi>Calumniator,</hi> that is to ſay in oure
engleſhe tonge a deprauer of euery thynge, for a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prauer properly is he
which dothe ſlaunderuſly accuſe, drepraue, and fautye that thyng that is
faucles: wherin this wycked ſpirit paſſeth and excellyth all, ſuch
thynges as god dothe teach &amp; commaund vs thoo thynges he corruptyth,
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauyth &amp; expoundyth them other wiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they bee. And this feyt he
fyrſt practiſed in paradiſe, in the fyrſt creation when god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
we ſhuld not touche nor taſte of the tree that grewe in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb facs="tcp:9435:22"/>of paradiſe. How craftly &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſly he expounded the
worde of god. Do you thynke, ſayd he, that god dyd forbyd you to eat thys. No
you ſhall not dye: thus he tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the trueth in to a lye, &amp; made god a
deuyll: the ſame thyng alſo he practiſeth dayly in oure conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
when he crepeth in and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyth oure hartes, he maketh them ſo ſecure
with out all remor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and feare as though they had neuer ſynned in all
theyr lyfe: the ſame he practiſed alſo at the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall counſell in the
cytie Anguſta, in hys byſſhoppes and prynces. But then moſt chefly he
playeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of a deuyll, and a deprauer, when he recyteth vp to good men
all theyr ſinnes, and makyth them much more greuous than they be. In thys
poynt he can ſo depraue and fauty all thy doctrine and all thy lyuyng that he
wyll make the<pb facs="tcp:9435:22"/>aborre thy ſelfe, and bewayle that euer thou
couldyſt letter in the boke. This is the very poynt and practiſe of the
deuyll: thys is the worke and the only ſtuddy of that wycked ſpirit: to
peruerte and cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupt thynges though they be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo good. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary wiſe
agayne the good Angelles, do take all thynges to the beſt, expoundyng euery
thynge in the honeſt parte, do comfort vs, do prouyde for vs, do ayde vs, do
defende vs, &amp; teach vs. Theſe thynges ought we to conſider and to gyue
god thankes therfore with all diligence, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery daye that we ryſe, to
make ſome ſuche prayer vnto god, as thys. O father of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I beſeche
the, that thy good angell may be with me thys day to kepe me, to gyde me, to
gouerne me, to preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue me and teach me et c.</p>
            <p>Of the great diligence and mynd<pb facs="tcp:9435:23"/>of the angelles toward
vs &amp; oure helth, we haue a goodly example in the boke of kynges, where as
Elezeus the prophet dyd ſhewe to hys miniſter great fyery hylles whiche
were ſet full of charettes and horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the which ſyght he perceiued
that his enemis were not to be fered whan there were many moo Angelles and
muche ſtronger than hys enemies were. Truth it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the good Angels be moch
more redy and glad to helpe and further vs the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked ſpy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rites be to
hurt and hyndre vs. Beſyds that there be many moo good Angelles than there be
yll: the good Angelles be euer ſuer &amp; diligent to do that which is
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them, that is, they kepe &amp; defende vs both truly &amp;
careful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly: wherfore though the deuyll be neuer ſo ſert to hurt or to
deſtroy vs, &amp; though he rore neuer ſo ſore<pb facs="tcp:9435:23"/>agaynſt vs,
yet be the good angel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les muche more diligent to aſſiſte and defende vs,
breuely, be euer more tender and carefull ouer vs, with theyr redy ſeruice to
do vs good. Thys we ought to lerne and know / for that ſhall cauſe vs that
we ſhall not be ſo ſecure and ſo ſlogyſhe in oure ſelues, but be
more circumſpect and better loke about vs and that we ſhall lerne the
better to beleue and truſt in god, whan we knowe that we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue many moo good
Angelles of our ſyde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuylles agaynſt vs, and be always of good chere
and comfort in all our affayers, in all oure afflictions, trobles, and
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſytes, ſayng with the prophet Elezeus: we haue many mo war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryers on
our part, than enemyes agaynſt vs. And ſo ſhall we ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the deuyll,
as Elezeus dyd ouercome his enemies, beyng bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<pb facs="tcp:9435:24"/>in the darknes
of theyr mynd, and we hauyng oure eys ſeyght ſhall bryng in oure ſowdiers
in to the citie of theyr aduerſaris / as we rede that Elezeus dyd in the
ſame chapiter. Theſe examples be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld prayſe
god and gyue hym thankes, for that, that he hath ſo appoynted for vs ſuche
an hoſt and an armie of hys holly angelles for oure defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſaffete,
ſo that yf one angell be not ynoughe, there ſhulde thowſands be redy by
and by, ſo as we ſe here in Elizeus, for whoſe only cauſe ſo many
thouſands of holy angelles dyd ſhew themſelfes &amp; dyd muſtre before
hym, redy at all tymes to ſuccour him whan nede ſhuld be. The very ſame
thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g weſe in Luke where fyrſte one angell came and ſhewed the byrthe of
Chriſte, but ſone after there was a multitude of the armye of angelles,
ſyngyng<pb facs="tcp:9435:24"/>with that one angell. et. c. Suche a multitude and a
whole armie of good Angells there be that God hathe apoynted for oure
ſoccoure and ſauegarde.</p>
            <p>Wherfore yf we vſe to thanke god for temporall peace, for good
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, &amp; officers, and for ſuche other worldly comodites. Than
how muche more ought we to gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue god prayſe and thankes for his good angelles
whyche he ſendyth to helpe vs, not only in bodely &amp; external thiges, but
alſo in al our ſpirituall affayres. For why they do both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme our fayth
in god, and alſo kepe vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of god: ſo theyr kepyng and
goodneſſe it is, that where we ſee one man dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the craft
and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation of the deuyll, we ſee a thouſand and a thouſande ſayued
agayne. Truly moo men there be always that lyue, then that dye. Therfore
<pb facs="tcp:9435:25"/>where thou ſeeſt any Cytie, any towne, any houſe ſayffe or
ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dig, there mayſt thou perceiue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good angelles be there to ſtoppe
the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl ſpirites that they diſtroy them not. Thus allways we ſee and
proue by experience, more good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euylls to be ſent vnto vs: As we
ſee in a bryghte daye / the ſonne to ſhynne much more cleare and
lyghtſome, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the blackenes of the nyght tyme is darke. Thus doth god make
vs to ſee his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytes and good turnes, which he beſtowyth vpon vs
through hys holly angelles, for to comforte vs and confyrme vs with all, that
we may vnderſtand by that meanes the wonderous deceyts, ſubteltes, and
damages of the deuyll, to the entent that we all ways ſhuld ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in feare,
and awe, and neuer to be ſecure and neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in our ſelues. Therfore lett
vs lerne thys well,<pb facs="tcp:9435:25"/>and bett in alſo to oure children, that they
may lerne thus to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort and ſtrenghthen them ſelues with the ayde of
theyr good a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles, &amp; ſo that they may lerne to feare the deuyll. And in
thys maner they owght to be brought vp with lyke information as this, or ſuch
other lyke. My child thou muſt not take the name af thy lord in vayn: thou
muſt not backbytte thy neyg boure: thou muſt not name the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyll, nor
muche haue hym in thy mouthe, for he is att hand in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, and is hard
by, &amp; about the wher ſoeuer thou goeſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les thou take hede, and
feare god, and employ thy ſelfe to goodneſſe and vertue, he wyll other
caſt the in the water to drowne the, or els he wyl be ſuer to do the ſum
great myſcheffe or other. And agayn leſt they ſhulde be brought in to to
much feare of him or to weakhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<pb facs="tcp:9435:26"/>in them ſelues thereby.
Theſe wycked ſpirites, My ſonne, as I tolde the, be allways about the,
&amp; greattly deſyrous to noy the ſome way or other, but oure lorde god
hath ordened good angels agayn an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre, and they be euer redy at
hande, yf thou be a good and an obidient child, to kepe the and preſerue the.
what ſo euer the deuyll goyth about, other to caſte the in the water to
drounde the, or to fray the in thy ſlepe, or to breke thy necke, et c.</p>
            <p>Moreouer in ſo much as we muſt feyght and warre with the
deuyll, it is requiſyt that we ſhuld know fyrſt what he is and how myghty
he is. No man can campe well w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the emnye whom he knowyth not. Now what maner
and ſorte he is of I haue ſhewed you, before. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo I haue ſhewed you,
howe he is a ſpiritt whiche neuer reſtyth nor<pb facs="tcp:9435:26"/>ceaſyth,
whoſe labore and ſtudy is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g els but to diſturbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace of the
world, to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in bataylles, to ſtyre vp inſurrections, ſtryf and
ſeditions, to make tumultes, and confuſion amongſte men: he can not
reſt nether can he wyll well to no man. It greuyth hym I dare ſay that I
make this ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nowe, and ſore it goeth to hys hart, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng more, yea it
greuyth hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my lyfe induryth a quarter of an ower: he hath conſpired and
leyed wayte for my death, and at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghth wyll dyſpatche me. But what ſhuld
I doo? Truly nothyng els but ſtycke only to the word of god and pray. O
father of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou ſeyſt and perceiuyſte what the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll goeth
about, ſend downe thy good Angell, to ſtoppe hys wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked purpoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he
haue no power in any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to hurt any body, but to the health and
euerlaſtyng ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation<pb facs="tcp:9435:27"/>to my ſoule. Amen. Thas ought we in
lyke maner to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our ſelues to god euery day: thus we ought alſo to
informe our chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may lykwiſe lerne to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend them ſelues
to god after the ſame maner. And ſo whan we do inſtruct our children thus
ſtyll ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomyng them to the ſame, they may turne to good men, and
lerne to feare god. Lykwiſe as children do hange of theyr parentes,
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectes of their magiſtrates, haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all theyr ſuccoure and prouydyng
by them: ſo do we hange of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, to whom god hath apoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the
promiſion and coſtody ouer vs. And ſo by that reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hathe ſo
apoynted his angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, to ſee to vs and ſuccoure vs, we may well
vnderſtand that we haue a perilous enemie about vs, euer redy and laboryng to
diſtroy vs. For els what nede we y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayde<pb facs="tcp:9435:27"/>and coſtodie of ſo
many Angelles, vnleſſe we were in great daunger of ſtrong &amp; myghtie
aduerſaries? wherfore it is our ꝑtes euermore to gyue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to god,
and to ſay. O heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father the father of all gentylnes, thankes, prayſe,
and glory be to the, for that, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght and ſuccour of thy
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles I am able to withſtand all the wicked ſpirites, whiche
not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of myne owne pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, am not able to withſtande the
weykeſt one of them, no though I had an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mo to helpe
me. Alſo that notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge myne enemy is ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng crafty
&amp; ſubtile, that I haue not one drope of craft where y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hathe a whole
ſeefull: yet through the protection and cuſtody of thy holy angelles, he
hathe no power to do me any wrong or vilany. My poore wiſedome, thoughe it
<pb facs="tcp:9435:28"/>yet but very ſmalle, and ſymple, dothe confound the hye and
great wiſedome of his, and all through thy mere grace &amp; the help of thy
ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Angelles, my Lord God Amen. And ſo thys is the glory of oure Lord God,
that he declaryth and ſettyth forth his glory, his wiſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, his power, in
our vnablenes, in oure foolyſhnes, and infirmite. This honor is only dewe to
him, that he is a god of might, power, of heygh wiſedome, and infinite
goodneſſe. And that thing he well declaryth, in that, that he ſendyth vs
hys helpe and defence by hys holy Angelles, ſo that we be able to ſtand
agynſt al the mayne hoſt &amp; armye, all the proude garde of the wycked
Angelles aboue, to ouercome them, to ouerthrowe them and gloriouſly to
triumphe vpon them. Chriſte Ieſus voutch ſaue euermore to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs al
with<pb facs="tcp:9435:28"/>his helpe and powre. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Prayſe be to God for euer Amen.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
